Guide to the Hudson Gurney, Miscellanea Historica
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
[Miscellanea historica: Collection of papers of historical interest relating to the reigns of James I and Charles I]
1601-1700
OSBORN FB164
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.13
(1 volume)
Manuscript, in multiple secretary hands, of a collection of 19 Parliamentary documents, primarily concerning the marriage negotiations between Charles I and the Spanish Infanta Maria. These include the petition of John Digby, Earl of Bristol, asking leave to defend his actions in the Spanish negotiations against his accusers; the information of Thomas, Baron Coventry presented to the House of Lords against Digby; and King Charles I's letter to Digby charging him with misconduct regarding the Spanish match. Also included are the abstract of articles presented by Digby against George Villiers, Duke of Buckingham; Buckingham's impeachment and defense, and a letter by King Philip IV of Spain to Conde Olivares regarding the marriage negotiations.
Gurney, Hudson, 1775-1864
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a complete inventory of the contents of Osborn fb164. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Libel and slander -- England; Treason -- England; Trials -- England; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- Scotland; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- Spain; Great Britain -- Religious life and customs -- 17th century; Scotland -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Spain -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Commonplace books; Charles, King of England, I, 1600-1649; James, King of England, I, 1566-1625; Maria Anna, consort of Ferdinand III, Holy Roman Emperor, 1606-1646; Philip, King of Spain, IV, 1605-1665; Bankes, John, Sir, 1589-1644; Bastwick, John, 1593-1654; Bristol, John Digby, Earl of, 1580-1654; Buckingham, George Villiers, Duke of, 1592-1628; Burton, Henry, 1578-1648; Digges, Dudley, Sir, 1583-1639; Finch, John, Baron Finch of Fordwich, 1584-1660; Gurney, Hudson, 1775-1864; Olivares, Gaspar de Guzmán, conde-duque de, 1587-1645; Prynne, William, 1600-1669; Great Britain. Parliament
- Osborn fb164
  - ROE, SIR THOMAS, 1581-1644
    - [Sir Thomas Roe's report to the House of Commons on the treaty with the Scots, 1640 Nov 13], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      24 p.
      Contemporary MS copy.
      Printed in Nalson, Collection, v.i.,
      524.
      p.1-12.
  - FINCH, JOHN FINCH, 1ST BARON, 1584-1660
    - [The speech of the Lord Keeper at the opening of Parliament, 1640 April 13], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      20 p.
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 146.
      p.13-22.
  - CHARLES, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The King's speech at the opening of Parliament, 1625 June 18], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      1 p.
      Printed with some variations in
      Rushworth, v.i., 171.
      p.23.
  - SCOTLAND. CITIZENS.
    - [The petition of the Scots to King Charles I and the King's reply, 1640 Sept 4,5] (Box 1)
      2 p.
      Contemporary MS copy, some text lost.
      The Scot's justification for their
      invasion of England and the King's
      reply, asking for a more direct
      statement of their grievances.
      Rushworth, v.3, 1255.
      p.24-25.
  - DIGGES, SIR DUDLEY, 1583-1639
    - [Sir Dudley Digges' speech to a conference of both houses of Parliament, 1628 Apr 3], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      5 p.
      On the liberties of the subject.
      LJ, iii, 717.
      p.26-29.
  - JAMES I. KING OF BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [Declaration to Parliament on Spain, 1623/4 Mar 23], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      3 p.
      LJ, iii, 282.
      p.30-31.
  - BRISTOL, JOHN DIGBY, 1ST EARL OF, 1580-1653
    - [Petition to the House of Lords, 1626 Apr 19], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Asks leave to defend himself against
      his accusers.
      LJ, iii, 563.
      p.32.
  - COVENTRY, THOMAS COVENTRY, 1ST BARON, 1578-1640
    - [Information presented to the House of Lords concerning the Earl of Bristol, 1626 Apr 21], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Requests the House to hear the
      charges against John Digby, 1st earl
      of Bristol.
      LJ, iii, 567.
      p.32v.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Letter to the Earl of Bristol], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1625/6 Feb 20]
      The King charges John Digby, 1st earl
      of Bristol with misconduct regarding
      the Spanish match. Rushworth, i, 237.
      p.33.
  - BRISTOL, JOHN DIGBY, 1ST EARL OF, 1580-1653
    - [An abstract of the articles presented by the Earl of Bristol against the Duke of Buckingham], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1676 May 1]
      Full articles in LJ, iii, 576.
      p.34.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1676.
    - [The humble remonstrance of the peers to the King regarding the Earl of Arundel] (Box 1)
      [1626 Apr 19]
      Petition to the King asking that
      Thomas Howard, 2nd earl of Arundel,
      be allowed to take his seat in the
      House of Lords.
      LJ, iii, 564.
      p.35.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1626.
    - [Impeachment of the Duke of Buckingham and the Duke's defense] (Box 1)
      [1626 May-June]
      205 p.
      Contemporary MS copies, various
      hands. Documents include the charges
      against George Villiers, 1st duke of
      Buckingham (1593-1628), the
      presentation of the case to the
      House of Lords by the managers of
      the impeachment (including Digges,
      Pym, Seldon, and Elliot), and the
      Duke's reply.
      LJ, iii and Rushworth, v.i.
      p. 36-146.
  - BUCKINGHAM, GEORGE VILLIERS, 1ST DUKE OF, 1592-1628
    - [Report of the Duke's speech to Parliament], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1623/4 Feb 24]
      7 p.
      A report on the Spanish marriage
      negotiations.
      See fb 155 for another copy.
      p. 147-151.
  - FELIPE IV, KING OF SPAIN, 1605-1665
    - [Letter to Conde Olivares on the marriage negotiations with the Prince of Wales] (Box 1)
      [1622 Nov 5]
      Contemporary MS copy, in English.
      Gaspar de Guzman, Conde-duque de
      Olivares, 1587-1645.
      LJ, iii, 226, and fb 155.
      p.152.
  - BRISTOL, JOHN DIGBY, 1ST EARL OF, 1580-1653
    - "The effect of certaine letters from the Earl of Bristol out of Spaine", [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [Jan 1623]
      On the Spanish marriage negotiations
      and recall of Bristol from Spain.
      Rushworth, v.i, 113.
      p.153.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Speech to a committee of Both Houses of Parliament], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1623/4 Mar 11]
      LJ, iii, 257, and fb 155.
      p.154.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1624
    - [The speech on the presentation of the subsidies], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1623/4 Mar 23]
      Includes notes of certain phrases
      with were removed by the King before
      the speech was inserted in the
      Journals.
      LJ, iii, 275.
      p.155.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PRIVY COUNCIL.
    - [Order in Council for a hearing on the dispute between Jeffrey Neve (1579-1654) and the town of Yarmouth] (Box 1)
      [1627 Nov 7]
      Dispute concerns Neve being ousted
      as alderman.
      p.156.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. COURT OF STAR CHAMBER.
    - [Information exhibited by Sir John Bankes (1589-1644) in the Court of Star Chamber], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1636/7 Mar 11]
      27 p.
      John Bastwick (1593-1654), Henry
      Burton (1578-1648), and William
      Prynne (1600-1669), are charged with
      publishing libels against the clergy
      and church.
      p.157-170.